A Guide to the Mary E. Ferguson Papers FA044
Rockefeller Archive Center
Mary E. Ferguson papers
1891, 1909-1975 (bulk 1950-1970)
bulk
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ferguson, Mary Esther
Rockefeller Foundation. China Medical Board
China Medical Board (U.S)
Rockefeller Foundation
FA044
3 Cubic Feet 8 boxes 1 oversized folder
Conditions Governing Access
Open for scholarly research without restriction.
Arrangement note
The Mary E. Ferguson papers are divided into three series:
Series 1 - Research Material
Series 2 - China Medical Board - Peking Union Medical College History Manuscript
Series 1046 - Photographs
Biographical/Historical note
Mary Esther Ferguson (1897-1989) was the registrar (1928-1950), assistant secretary (1930, 1932), and secretary (1933-1941, 1944-1950) of the Peking Union Medical College, and associate secretary of the United Boards for Christian Higher Education in China (1950-1960).
Scope and Contents note
The material in the Mary E. Ferguson papers deals with the research, writing, and publication of "China Medical Board - Peking Union Medical College: A Chronicle of Fruitful Collaboration, 1914-1915," published in New York, 1970. The strength of the collection lies in the primary source documents: interviews with former staff at the Peking Union Medical College (PUMC), correspondence relating to the book's conception through publication, and reports of China during the Japanese occupation and after nationalization in 1951. Much of the research correspondence had been photocopied from the files of the China Medical Board, Inc., and the Rockefeller Foundation. (The book is an administrative history of PUMC, and most of the research material deals with the staff and administration of the institution.)
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IV 2A 23
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Mary E. Ferguson gave her papers to the Rockefeller Archive Center in 1977 and September 1979.
China; Peking. Union Medical College; Ferguson, Mary Esther; Rockefeller Foundation. China Medical Board; China Medical Board (U.S); Rockefeller Foundation
- Research Material, 1891-1971; 1; 1.6 Cubic Feet
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged in six subseries:
  Subseries 1 - General Information
  Subseries 2 - Notes
  Subseries 3 - Correspondence
  Subseries 4 - Interviews
  Subseries 5 - Miscellaneous Research
  Subseries 6 - Notebooks
  - General Information, 1
    Scope and Contents note
    This subseries contains printed and primary sources, including material relating to the Japanese takeover and occupation of China (1941-1943), the China Medical Board's War Claim (1960-1964), reprints from the China Medical Journal (1909-1922), and reports of 'thought reform' in the Chinese People's Republic (1948-1971).
    - China, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Japanese Takeover of China and Peking Union Medical College (PUMC) - Reports, December 8, 1941-September 15, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - China Medical Board (CMB) War Claim, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Chinese People's Republic "Thought Reform", 1948-May 27, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Chinese People's Republic "Thought Reform", 1948-May 27, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - China Medical Journal Reprints, 1909-1922 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Printed Material, 1914-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Peking Union Medical College (PUMC) Architecture (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - F. T. Gates, 1891-1921 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Notes, 2
    - Peking Union Medical College (PUMC) Personnel (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Peking Union Medical College (PUMC) Personnel - Diary Excerpts (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Roger S. Greene (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Peking Union Medical College (PUMC) Post-War Rehabilitation, 1946-1951 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Peking Union Medical College (PUMC)-China Medical Board (CMB) Administrative Reports (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Peking Union Medical College (PUMC)-China Medical Board (CMB) Administrative Reports (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Budget and Exchange Rates (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Medical Schools in China (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Index Cards (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Chart of Rockefeller Foundation - China Medical Board - Peking Union Medical College Officers, Large format material, housed in map folder. (Box F 134, Folder 1)
    - Bus Map of Peking, Large format material, housed in map folder. (Box F 134, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1918-1950; 3
    Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, Roger S. Greene, Alan Gregg, Henry S. Houghton, and George E. Vincent.
    - Correspondence, 1918-April 1938 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1918-April 1938 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1918-April 1938 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, 1918-April 1938 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, March 1938-1950 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, March 1938-1950 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Notes from Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Interviews, 4
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (audio tape) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
    Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services / Head of Reference.
    - Dunlap, Albert Menzo (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Hodges, Paul C. (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Houghton, Henry S. (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Macmillan, Eva B. (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Snapper, Isidore (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Wilson, Stanley (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Wolf, Anna D. (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - "Group at St. Petersburg" (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Audio Tape - Interview with Anna Wolf, Faye Whiteside, Tom and Robin, St. Petersburg, Florida, March 22, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Audio Tape - Interview with Henry S. Houghton, June 14 and 15, [1961?]; Tape 1 of 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Audio Tape - Interview with Henry S. Houghton, June 28, 1961; Tape 2 of 2 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Research, 5
    - Miscellaneous Research (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Notebooks, 6
    - Notebook Additions (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Notebooks, 12 (Box 4, Folder 35A)
- China Medical Board - Peking Union Medical College History Manuscript, 1950-1975; 2; 1.2 Cubic Feet
  This series is arranged in three subseries:
  Subseries 1 - Chapter Drafts
  Subseries 2 - Mechanics of the Book
  Subseries 3 - Material Relating to the Publication
  - Chapter Drafts, 1
    - 'The Storm Breaks' (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - 'The War Years' (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - 'Beginning Again' (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - 'A New Storm Gathers', 1948 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - 'Adjustment to a New Era', 1948 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - 'The Last Days of the Old Era' (Chapter 10) (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - 'Dr. Houghton's Resignation', 1927 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Chapter Three (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - 'The Pre-Medical School' (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - 'Peking Union Medical School (PUMC) Budget and Exchange Rates', 1930-1931 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - 'Sun-Yat Sen' - Correspondence, Notes (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - 'School of Nursing' - Not Published (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Miscellaneous Chapter Rewrites (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - XVII - The Peking Union Medical College (PUMC) Trustees vs. The China Medical Board (CMB) (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - XXI-XXIV - The Storm Breaks, The War Years, Beginning Again (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - XXV-XXVIII - Renascence, A New Storm Gathers, Adjustment to a New Era, The Last Days of the Old Era (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Draft - Volume I (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Draft - Volume II (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Draft (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Mechanics of the Book, 2
    The mechanics subseries includes chronologies, chapter sequences, and footnotes.
    - Chronology (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Chapter Sequence (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Footnotes (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Footnotes (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Material Relating to the Publication, 3
    Material in Subseries 3 includes requests for records from the archives of the institutions involved, requests for the history, comments on the book and correspondence covering the period of time from conception to publication of the book (1950-1975).
    Correspondents include Mary E. Ferguson, Harold Loucks, Paul Hodges, Franklin McLean, and Henry S. Houghton.
    - Requests for Material, Progress Reports (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Correspondence - Requests for History (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - Correspondence - Requests for History (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - Correspondence - Comments - Former Faculty, Staff, Graduates (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - Correspondence - Criticisms, Omissions (Box 6, Folder 63)
    - Reviews of History (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - Final Draft (Box 6A, Folder 64A)
    - Final Draft (Box 6A, Folder 64B)
    - Final Draft (Box 6A, Folder 64C)
    - Final Draft (Box 6A, Folder 64A)
    - Final Draft (Box 6A, Folder 64B)
    - Final Draft (Box 6A, Folder 64C)
    - Correspondence - General, 1950-1953, 1957-1975 (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - Correspondence - General, 1950-1953, 1957-1975 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - Correspondence - General, 1950-1953, 1957-1975 (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - Correspondence - General, 1950-1953, 1957-1975 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Correspondence - General, 1950-1953, 1957-1975 (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Correspondence - General, 1950-1953, 1957-1975 (Box 7, Folder 70)
    - Correspondence - General, 1950-1953, 1957-1975 (Box 7, Folder 71)
- Mary E. Ferguson photographs, 1046
  Ferguson, Mary Esther; Ferguson, Mary E.
  - Mary E. Ferguson (Box 22, Folder 278)